[SPEAKER_03]: So, say somebody is keeping the precepts, training in the eight precepts, practicing sense restraint, you know, household, the monk, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: The question is, are there times where it's more or less appropriate for thinking and contemplating things
[SPEAKER_03]: The citta doesn't want to think about.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, are there times where you should force it to think about things?
[SPEAKER_03]: Are there times where you should, like, okay, now I won't...
[SPEAKER_03]: I won't be forcing it?
[SPEAKER_03]: How to discern where that line is?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you should force it if you see that if you leave it alone, it's going to start inclining towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: You will delight in the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it's slant at the moment, then you need to do something about that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if you see that is not there, if I just leave the mind on its own, it's not going to move towards those things, then you actively trying to kind of force you to think about it, will just be like hitting an animal that's not misbehaving.
[SPEAKER_03]: If without... if you choose to not contemplate, you already know, it's already implicit that by not bringing up certain topics, the mind will continue, the animal will continue walking outside of the boundaries, mentally, verbally, and then eventually physically.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you bring up those reflections, topics, death, illness, the unpleasant stuff that the mind doesn't want to think about, liabilities and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: You bring that up to the extent just to undo, neutralize that passion towards walking towards the pastures it shouldn't go.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if it's not walking there, you should actually not bring it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't be like,
[SPEAKER_03]: Blindly bound with the duty of I must contemplate and bring it up regardless of the basis or the state of the mind where it's in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that will then be... that sense of duty will then be the strongest inclination that's dominating you at the time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it will be... that will come out of the mind being restless.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you look where your mind is at.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without bringing up contemplations, like, oh, is it leaning towards sensuality, complacency, laziness, or... no, it seems alright, seems balanced enough, then I don't need to bring anything up.
[SPEAKER_03]: When it starts to lean, you will know.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because I think the problem is, you might expect a super-defined confirmation that it's not leaning in those ways, but it's just the absence of leaning in those is the confirmation.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the kind of that peripheral discernment you have to keep working on, and getting the hints of is it leaning or not, not the specific palpable proofs.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not gonna tell you like, oh, I'm not leaning anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, because that's not where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess I've often heard people ask similar questions and something that's brought up is the second arrow and then how someone could turn their kind of contemplations into this kind of, oh, who shot me?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have to think about my whole past or understand... Well, that actually...
[SPEAKER_03]: That would fall under the very... well, under what you said.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if, say, some suffering arose and you're pressured to analyze it, who, what, why, how to prevent it, that's mind going into the wrong pastures already.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a full-on obsessive pressure, irritation, compulsion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, so now I should not think about those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: I should just
[SPEAKER_03]: Pull the mind back, basically, not let it, not provide it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and that's... that's what it's about, developing the criteria of the mind as the thing that determines the practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas, when you don't see that, yeah, you will take on this duty of contemplating things as if that, independently, is an ideal, is what needs to be done, rather than seeing it's only... only to the extent that it influences the mind does that need to be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you... the mind is where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not in the fact that you fail to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do I... how do I see my mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I get to see that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, ask yourself what is, like you said before, what is the main kind of effortless inclination that... that would present itself without you putting it there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if now,
[SPEAKER_04]: The thing that I'm being pulled towards is contemplating, not sensuality, or will.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, those are the signs of your mind now.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's whatever is manifesting...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, should I contemplate in that specific scenario?
[SPEAKER_03]: If I'm pulled towards contemplating?
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you shouldn't do what the mind is pulling you to do, but if you're afraid of like, also, does that mean I'll become mindless?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well,
[SPEAKER_04]: You're already... the seeing of that pressure towards contemplation is what you should be reflecting on.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the more right contemplation.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if the mind is pulling you towards contemplation, don't just take it for granted and start walking with it in that direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: Contemplate the danger of doing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But recognize the pulling mind, doesn't matter what it's pulling you towards, and that's actually contemplation, just not in your own terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it also might be worth mentioning that
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a level of ambiguity that comes from not doing it on your own terms and so, yeah, because... Because it won't... it doesn't feel right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it feels more right to contemplate when the mind is pressuring you to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it feels kind of wrong to...
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, ask yourself, what type of feeling right is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is there the same feeling right of when it's inclining to a sensuality and you give in to that?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the type of feeling right.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because it's helping you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's helping you do that contemplation because that's where it wants to go already.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if that's what's happening, you realize, well, you're not taming it, you're giving in to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's like going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's literally the meaning of the expression.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, where the grain already is, you're going there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Feels right, because... To satisfy the compulsion, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what about if you've been training in contemplation every day, so on, you know, a long time, and then it's... that's what the mind enjoys doing now, uncovering things, uncovering issues, you know, your defilements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Am I liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, there's that one statement somewhere the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_02]: was that, eh, he knew two qualities when he was striving.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was discontent with unwholesome... With wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: With discontent with unwholesome states that... No, with wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_04]: With wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, with wholesome qualities.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Discontent with wholesome qualities and unrelenting... Effort, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it was like you would be contemplating, uncovering things, destroying defilements, asavas, virtuous and feeling
[SPEAKER_02]: The joy of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the mind is... this is great.
[SPEAKER_02]: And yet, is he saying, I'm discontent with that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he's seeing the mind's contentment, and then he's being discontent with that, and saying, well, no, we need to dig more here.
[SPEAKER_02]: We need to make more effort, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right, but always the thing would be like...
[SPEAKER_04]: It would be against the grain.
[SPEAKER_04]: It wouldn't be on your terms, that the mind wanted to uncover things, wanted to, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Be discontent, and you went with it.
[SPEAKER_04]: On account of that, it's... it's... the mind was going towards the direction of contentment, and then you need to actually make an effort to see, wait, even in this, there is still dissatisfaction, there is still inadequacy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Complacency.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the mind gets complacent, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Complacent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but of course, like, that would be complacent now with things that are actually wholesome.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's... it wouldn't be complacency with, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: A normal person being complacent with me would mean they would be tolerating sensuality and things like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, being complacent with your withdrawal from sensuality, which is not in itself arahantship, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, relentless effort, it's basically relentlessly not allowing actions out of any layer of compulsion.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not relentlessly grab the compulsion and run with it relentlessly, never stop, which is how initially it will be taken.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's like whenever compulsion is discerned, relentlessly, diligently, you never willingly accept it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You always reestablish perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if one can think about, contemplate and
[SPEAKER_03]: The... actually reflect on asavas and uncover asavas without any grain of compulsion coming from the mind, then, yes, that's what's meant with that pure, relentless training on the right level.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if one does it out of this, like, mental force of pressure, if I do it, I'll get rid of it, that's just...
[SPEAKER_03]: That kind of falls off the right context.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and if you ask yourself honestly, what takes more effort?
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: To not feed the compulsion.
[SPEAKER_03]: To go with it or to say no to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter what the object of it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if it's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, by not following the compulsion towards quote-unquote dhamma reflections, you are actually practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Non-passion, non-aversion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Non-restlessness.